Las Posadas Collection, 1943-2007 (bulk 1981-2007)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Las Posadas Collection, 1943-2007 (bulk 1981-2007)
MS 552
La Pilita Museum
Las Posadas collection contains material relating to Tucson, Arizona’s Carrillo Elementary School’s long tradition of re-enacting Mary and Joseph’s pilgrimage from Nazareth to Bethlehem in a procession seeking shelter or posada. This event was based on an old Mexican yuletide custom that was first adopted by Miss Marguerite Collier in 1937 to build students’ pride in their Hispanic heritage, and has since then become an annual celebration for all its students and the community.
2 Linear feet.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/ E-Mail: LBRY-askspcoll@email.arizona.edu
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
Las Posadas is a cultural tradition influenced by Christianity. It is a re-enactment of Mary and Joseph’s pilgrimage from Nazareth to Bethlehem, where Christ was born. This religious tradition based on the New Testament began in Spain, and was adopted in Mexico in the mid to late 1500’s by friars who looked to strengthen Christian beliefs and attract converts within the Aztecs. The original procession took nine days, each day representing a month of Mary’s pregnancy with Jesus, and began nine days before Christmas.
In 1937, Miss Marguerite Collier, a teacher at Carrillo Elementary School initiated the enactment of “Las Posadas” as a way to build pride amongst her Hispanic students. It has since then been her legacy to the school and the community, as the procession of costumed children singing Nativity songs has continued for over 75 years. Despite its controversial religious nature, the school has been able to continue the celebration making it an after school activity and not using school district funding. Important community collaboration has been incorporated throughout the years and has gained sponsorship from organizations such as the Tucson Festival Society and the DeGrazia Art & Cultural Foundation.
Throughout the years the procession has been held in the evenings in the historic Barrio El Hoyo where the school is located, and has included dramatization, caroling, and food, all organized by the school’s staff, students and community collaborators. The enactment consists of students dressing up as Mexican farmers and winged angels, and walking door-to-door asking for shelter or posada, while carrying candles and a Nativity scene. The children sing traditional carols, usually in Spanish, down the streets, which are blocked off. Community members are encouraged to join in since it is a free public event.
Arrangement
This collection is in chronological order.
Scope and Content Note
The collection (1943-2007, bulk 1981-2007), contains materials documenting the history of Carrillo Elementary School’s Las Posadas procession in Tucson, Arizona. It includes childrens’ artwork and writing, invitations, programs, event history, correspondence, photographs, publications, newspaper clippings related to the event, music books, song lyrics, class lists of participating students, colored slides and CD’s of Carrillo children performances, and a custom designed event t-shirt.
Access Terms
Collier, Marguerite .
Carrillo Intermediate Magnet School (Tucson, Ariz.).
Carrillo Intermediate Magnet School (Tucson, Ariz.).
Posadas (Social custom).
Tucson (Ariz.).
Container List
- Las Posadas, 1942-1943, 1955, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Las Posadas, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Las Posadas, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Las Posadas, 1970-1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Las Posadas, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Las Posadas, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Las Posadas, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Las Posadas, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Las Posadas, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Las Posadas, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Las Posadas, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Las Posadas, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Las Posadas, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Las Posadas, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Las Posadas, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Las Posadas, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Las Posadas, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Las Posadas, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Las Posadas, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Las Posadas, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Las Posadas, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Las Posadas, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Las Posadas, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Las Posadas, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Las Posadas, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Las Posadas, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Las Posadas, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Las Posadas, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Las Posadas, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Las Posadas, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Las Posadas, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Las Posadas, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Las Posadas, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Las Posadas, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Las Posadas, 2005-2007 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Las Posadas, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Published Song Books, 1950-1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)